<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>St. Paules-Church her bill for the Parliament as it was presented to the Kings Matie on Midlent-Sunday last, and intended for the view of that most high and honorable court, and generally for all such as beare good will to the reflourishing estate of the said church. Partly in verse, partly in prose. Penned and published for her good by Hen: Farley author of her complaint.</title>
            <author>Farley, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849893</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849893</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 790:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>St. Paules-Church her bill for the Parliament as it was presented to the Kings Matie on Midlent-Sunday last, and intended for the view of that most high and honorable court, and generally for all such as beare good will to the reflourishing estate of the said church. Partly in verse, partly in prose. Penned and published for her good by Hen: Farley author of her complaint.</title>
                  <author>Farley, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Eld for R. Milbourne],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. M. DC. XXI [1621]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse and prose. Advocating and celebrating the repair of St. Paul's Cathedral.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The title page and F1 verso each have a woodcut of St. Paul's with different verses in the scrolls. This woodcut is also found in STC 10688.5, where it has yet different verses in the scrolls--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F²  (A1 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>St. Paul's Cathedral (London, England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. PAVLES-CHVRCH HER BILL FOR THE <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> As it was preſented to the Kings Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> on <hi>Midlent-Sunday</hi> laſt, and intended for the view of that moſt high and Honorable Court, and generally for all ſuch as beare good will to the reflouriſhing eſtate of the ſaid CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Partly in Verſe, partly in Proſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Penned and publiſhed for her good by HEN: FARLEY Author of her Complaint.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>For the Lord will comfort Zion and repayre all her decayes: Hee will make her Deſert like Paradice, and her Wilderneſſe like the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Lord. Mirth and ioy ſhall bee found there, Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing and the praiſe of melody. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 51. 3.</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom. M. DC. XXI.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH Court of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">All bleſsings from the Higheſt be euer preſent in your high and Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Deſignes for CHVRCH and COMMON-WEALTH.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay your Wiſedomes be pleaſed to accept theſe my Labours as an humble ſuite out of my zeale, for the good of Gods Houſe. What honour ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crue therby, I will euer attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to his glory, and your goodneſſe; only intimating to your memories ſomething fitting to bee conſidered of at this time; not as an arrogant teacher, but as an humble Remembrancer. Neuer had any Church more need of Reparation and Reformation; for euery day ſhee conſumeth, and euery baſe fellow piſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her doores and defileth her walles, as if <hi>Shee</hi> only (who ſhould be the only <hi>She</hi> for <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample)</hi> were the only contempt and ſcorne of all the
<pb facs="tcp:15065:3"/> reſt. Her Weſt doore, and Brazen Pillar, where his Maieſtie kneeled, and prayed for good ſucceſſe to his Pious intendment for her reſtauration, is the moſt odiouſly and ignominiouſly abuſed; and becauſe there is no power by lawes and penalties to puniſh the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, they are ſo bold that none of her Officers, or others, dare controule them: I moſt humbly referre the conſideration thereof to your Graue Wiſedomes, it being the only cauſe that hath moued me to publiſh this worke. There are many of my Honorable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters among you <hi>(the Commiſſioners appointed by his Maieſty for the reparation of the ſaid Church)</hi> of whoſe furtherance in this and much more, I haue no doubt; and of whoſe noble fauours I haue had ſome taſte. So truſting in the Almighty they will continue the ſame, and humbly beſeeching your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, protection, and Patronage, I remaine in my Prayers as I firſt beganne,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Proſtrate at your feete in all loyall and humble obedience during life.</hi> H. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>S. PAVLES to the BOOKE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THoſe that reade thee with good will,</l>
               <l>As my friends reſpect them ſtill;</l>
               <l>But if Carpers wince, or ſtrike,</l>
               <l>Tell them they are gall'd belike.</l>
               <l>Sure I am my Authors minde</l>
               <l>Was to pleaſe in euery kinde,</l>
               <l>And his Worke well order'd is,</l>
               <l>If it be not ta'ne amiſſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The BOOKE to PAVLES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOt S. <hi>Peter,</hi> nor S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor our <hi>Sauiour</hi> could pleaſe all,</l>
               <l>Therefore let no man aliue,</l>
               <l>In that vaine of pleaſing ſtriue:</l>
               <l>I will gladly pleaſe each friend,</l>
               <l>And the reſt pray God amend.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>S.</hi> Paules <hi>her Reply.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THen be gone incontinent</l>
               <l>To the Court of Parliament,</l>
               <l>And in truth and reuerence,</l>
               <l>(Without filed Eloquence)</l>
               <l>Speake the beſt thou canſt for mee,</l>
               <l>So farewell, God proſper thee.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:4"/>
            <head>The Author breaking forth in ioy at this Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſaith in the behalfe of the Church and himſelfe, thus:</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF my Booke paſſe currant there,</l>
               <l>Then be gone all griefe and feare:</l>
               <l>For mine eyes ſhall ſhortly ſee</l>
               <l>What my ſoule long wiſht ſhould bee,</l>
               <l>To my hearts high exaltation,</l>
               <l>And the honor of our Nation,</l>
               <l>That's your ſpeedy reparation.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>Before S.</hi> Paules <hi>doth ſpeake any more, She ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth how ſhee may ſpeake, &amp;c. though but ſtone, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS it is ſaid that Ships doe fight,</l>
               <l>When tis the men that in them bee:</l>
               <l>So I (poore Church) pray, ſpeake, and write,</l>
               <l>When tis my Friend doth all for mee.</l>
               <l>For neuer yet could wood or ſtone</l>
               <l>Doe any of theſe things alone.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Poſie of ſundry Flowers and Herbes, gathered out of the Garden of Gods Word, knit vp together, and ſet in the Frontiſpice of this Worke, for the ſmell of euery good Reader, as a ſweet odour to the reſt that followes:</head>
            <p>
               <hi>It being full of diuine Caution and Example.</hi> (viz.)</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HAGGAI 1 <hi>Chap. Ver.</hi> 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His People ſay the <note n="*" place="margin">This is <hi>Blacke Time,</hi> and a fearefull hearb; If <hi>Hearb-grace,</hi> or Gods mercy, did not grow by it, to quench his anger with mans repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant teares, &amp;c.</note> Time is not yet come, that the Lords Houſe ſhould be builded.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Branches of this Time are many:</hi> (viz.)</p>
            <q>
               <p>Then came the Word of the Lord by the Miniſtery of the Prophet <hi>Haggai,</hi> ſaying:</p>
               <p>Is it time for your ſelues <hi>(O Yee)</hi> to dwell in your ſeiled houſes, and this <hi>Houſe</hi> lye waſte?</p>
               <p>Now thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes; Conſider your owne wayes in your hearts; ye haue ſowen much, but ye bring in little; ye eate, but ye haue not enough; ye drinke, but ye are not filled; ye cloath you, but ye be not warme; and he that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:15065:5"/> wages, putteth it into a broken bagge.</p>
               <p>Get you vp into the Mountaine, and fetch <note place="margin">In this branch (being the middle branch) doth Gods mercy appeare, (if man will be warned.)</note> wood and build this Houſe, and I will be glorified, and I will take pleaſure in it, ſaith the Lord; <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 6. 10. That ye may haue to offer ſweet Sauors to the God of Heauen, and pray for the Kings life and for his Children.</p>
               <p>Ye looked for much, and loe, it came to little; and when ye brought it home, I did blow vpon it, And why (ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes?) becauſe of my houſe that is waſte, and yee runne euery man into his owne <note n="*" place="margin">If the <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> and <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti-call</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of this time, would but ſmell well to this Branch, they might learne to loue me their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church much more then they doe; I meane as I am an ancient houſe of God.</note> houſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore vpon you the Heauen is ſtaied from Dew, and the Earth is ſtaied from yeilding her increaſe.</p>
               <p>And I haue called for a drought vpon the Land, and vpon the Mountaines, and vpon the Corne, and vpon the Wine, and vpon the Oyle, and vpon all that the Earth bringeth forth; vpon Men, and vpon Cattell, and vpon all the labour of the hands.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Zorobabel</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Salathiel,</hi> and <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ioſedech</hi> the high Prieſt, with all the remnant of the People, heard the voice of the Lord their God, and the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Haggai,</hi> as the Lord their God had ſent him:</p>
               <p>Then the People did <note n="*" place="margin">This Herbe may well be called <hi>Sage,</hi> or <hi>Sapience,</hi> for the Feare of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdome.</note> feare before the Lord.</p>
               <p>And the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> &amp;c. and the ſpirit of all the People, and they came and did the worke in the houſe of the Lord of Hoſtes, their God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. 27. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Lord God of our Fathers, which <note place="margin">This is <hi>Carduu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Benedictus,</hi> or <hi>Bleſſed Thiſtle.</hi>
                  </note> hath put ſuch things as theſe into the heart of our good King, to beautifie the houſe of the Lord which is in Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24. 8. 9. 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And at the Kings commandement they made a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Penny Royall,</hi> or the Kings Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Penny or gift.</note> Cheſt, and ſet it without at the gate of the houſe of the Lord; and made a Proclamation through Iuda and Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And the Lords and all the People reioyced, and <note place="margin">This may be called <hi>Angelica,</hi> when Angels are ſo offered.</note> brought in vntill there was ſufficient, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. <hi>Kings</hi> 12. 9. 10. 11. 12.</bibl>
               <p>But <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> the high Prieſt tooke a Cheſt, <note place="margin">This is (as I take it) <hi>Burſa Paſtoris,</hi> or <hi>Shepheards purſe</hi> or the <hi>Clergies Cheſt.</hi>
                  </note> and bored a hole in the lid of it, and ſet it beſide the Altar, on the right ſide, as euery man cometh into the Temple of the Lord, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And when they ſaw there was much money in the Cheſt, the Kings Scribe, and the high prieſt came vp and told the money, &amp;c. and gaue it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into the hands of them that executed the worke, and ſuch as had the ouerſight of the houſe of the Lord. Thus they did day by day, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered money in abundance. And ſo the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wrought, and the worke amended through their hands, and they made the houſe of God as it ought to be, and ſtrengthned it. So <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Thus farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the pious branches of the good herbe called the <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards Purſe.</hi>
                  </note> waxed old, and died full of dayes, &amp;c. And they buried him in the City of <hi>Dauid,</hi> among the Kings, becauſe he dealt well with Iſrael, and with God and his Houſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:6"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Here followeth</hi> Mother-Time, <hi>gathered by the good King of our time, and ſent to the Reuerend Kingly Biſhop, Phyſitian, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Mother-Church, as an Herbe of moſt excellent vertue to cure all her diſeaſes.</hi> (viz.)</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme</hi> 102. <hi>verſes</hi> 13. 14.</bibl>
               <p>THou ſhalt ariſe and haue mercy vpon Sion, for the <note n="*" place="margin">This ſweet <hi>Mother</hi> or <hi>Mountaine Time</hi> may alſo be called the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ointment vpon the head, that ran downe vnto our <hi>Aarons</hi> beard: yea euen to the skirts of his Clothing: or yet more properly, like the Dew of <hi>Hermon,</hi> which (by a diuine Sermon) fell vpon our ſacred hill of <hi>Sion.</hi>
                  </note> Time to fauour her, yea the ſet time is come.</p>
               <p>For thy ſeruants take pleaſure in her ſtones, and fauour the duſt thereof.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Parallel of preſent time with time paſt: Or, of a good King liuing, with a faithfull good King long ſince deceaſed.</head>
            <p>IN the 18. yeare of the reigne of our good King <hi>Iames</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Ouer Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France, and Ireland.</note>, it pleaſed his ſacred Maieſtie to viſit me (poore Church) and ſoone after to ſend the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of his City, with diuers of his Nobles, Reuerend Fathers, and Elders, to ſuruey my wants, and to returne vnto his Highneſſe all my diſeaſes and corruptions, and their cauſes; that ſo he might (like a moſt excellent <note n="b" place="margin">Supreame head &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth within his Maieſties Dominions.</note> Phyſitian next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God) take courſe for my cure. And ſo in the ſame yere he called a Parliament intending firſt to purge the land and the Temple, and then (I hope) to ſend his Nobles, &amp;c. againe, that ſhall neuer ceaſe till I bee totally cured, and moſt beautifully repayred.</p>
            <p>This may then be worthily paralleld with the noble acts of that famous and faithfull King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> recorded and renowned in the ſecond Booke of the <hi>Kings,</hi> the 22. Chapter, and in the ſecond <note place="margin">Verſes 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. &amp;c. Verſes 8, 9, 10. &amp;c.</note> Booke of <hi>Chron.</hi> the 34. Chapter.</p>
            <p>For in the 18. yeare of his Reigne (when hee had purged the Land and the Temple of Hereſie <note place="margin">This is heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hyſope.</note> and Corruption) <note n="c" place="margin">It ſhould ſeem this was at the end of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was a heauenly concluſion of one good worke, and a moſt ſacred beginning of another. <hi>Nota quaeſo, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> he ſent <hi>Saphan</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Azaliah,</hi> and <hi>Maaſiah</hi> the Gouernor of the City,
<pb facs="tcp:15065:7"/> and <hi>Ioah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ioahaz</hi> the Recorder, to repaire the Houſe of the Lord his God, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And when they came to <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the high prieſt, they deliuered the money that was brought into the houſe of God, which the Leuites that kept the Entries had gathered of the hands of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> &amp; <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and of all that yet remained in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of all <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Beniamin,</hi> and they returned to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> and they put it in the hands of them <note place="margin">Men did not then come like Beares to a ſtake to ſuch a buſineſſe, but like poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to a xij<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. dole. Happy was hee that could doe any thing which might dignifie and ſet forward the worke.</note> that had the ouerſight of the houſe of the Lord, and they gaue it to the Laborers that wrought in the houſe of the Lord, to repaire and mend the Houſe: euen to Maſons and Carpenters gaue they it to get hewed ſtone and timber for Couples and for Beames, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the men did worke, &amp;c. And the Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of them to courage them forward, were <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hath</hi> and <hi>Obadiah,</hi> Leuits of the Children of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari;</hi> and <hi>Zechariah,</hi> and <hi>Meſhullam</hi> of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Kohathites,</hi> which all could skill of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of muſicke:</p>
            <p>And ouer the bearers of burthens, and ouer all that wrought in whatſoeuer workmanſhip, were there Scribes, Officers, and Porters of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus farre the Poſie of heauenly Herbs and Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, gathered out of the Garden where mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions more might haue beene culled for my purpoſe, but I hope this is enough to him that delighteth in ſweet Odours of piety and good workes.</p>
            <p>And to that end I will pray as followeth.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>This Prayer or Petition is for the King, Prince, &amp;c. and directed to the King of Kings.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O King of Kings, and Lord Omnipotent,</l>
                  <l>Direct, protect King <hi>Iames</hi> in Parliament;</l>
                  <l>Make all thoſe wholeſome Lawes he treats vpon,</l>
                  <l>T'approue him ſtill, a ſecond <hi>Salomon;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A bleſſed <hi>Peacemaker,</hi> Churches Amender:</l>
                  <l>And (in Great <hi>Britaine</hi> long) <hi>true Faiths Defender.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That euery Pen may write a ſacred Story</l>
                  <l>Of all his Noble Acts, done to thy Glory:</l>
                  <l>And Sinne (corrupt and baſe) may (out of hand)</l>
                  <l>Be purged quite and cleane out of the Land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His <hi>Sonne</hi> (likewiſe) thy Sonne (O God) ſo guide him,</l>
                  <l>That all good hopes and haps may ſtill betide him;</l>
                  <l>And as he is a Prince of prudent carriage.</l>
                  <l>So bleſſe him (Lord) in <hi>Single life</hi> and <hi>Marriage;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make him thy Iem of Iems, thy Pearle of Pearles,</l>
                  <l>(Next to his Maieſty) our <hi>Princely Charles;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy conqu'ring Champion when he goes to Warres,</l>
                  <l>(As he is Conqu'rer at the Tilting-barres;)</l>
                  <l>And thy ſtrong <hi>Sampſon</hi> (valiant in the Field,)</l>
                  <l>That he may fight and kill, and ne're be kild.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bleſſe alſo all his noble Lords and Peeres,</l>
                  <l>His Biſhops, Burgeſſes, and Knights of Shires,</l>
                  <l>And giue them Ioy, Proſperity, and Health,</l>
                  <l>That doe their beſt for <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-Wealth.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let not any man be ſo vnholy,</l>
                  <l>From henceforth for to beg a <note n="*" place="margin">I meane ſuch as are helpfull to one Subiect, and hurtfull to all the reſt.</note> Monopoly:</l>
                  <l>For well I wote, Much-ill proceeds thereby,</l>
                  <l>It wrongs the STATE, and ſokes the Subiects drie;</l>
                  <l>Hardens mens hearts, all good <note n="b" place="margin">I doubt it hath a little choked mens good deuotions towards me.</note> deſignes doth choke,</l>
                  <l>And (ſuch as pinch) doth to reuenge prouoke;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"(A thing inhumane, that one Chriſtian Brother,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"Or fellow Subiect, ſhould deuoure another.)</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And for my <hi>Soueraignes</hi> loue to me laſt Lent,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a Holy day diuinely ſpent;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:8"/>
                  <l> Loue him (good Lord) and let him plainely ſee,</l>
                  <l>It's much the more for his great loue to mee;</l>
                  <l>That ſo his Highneſſe may (without Omiſſion)</l>
                  <l>Moſt royally proceed in the Commiſſion</l>
                  <l>By Him appointed for my Reſtauration,</l>
                  <l>Vpon my humble Plaint and Supplication;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"For neuer came more honor to a King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"Then my repayre will to his Highneſſe bring:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"Nor can a worke be of more note or name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>"To raiſe Him and His ſeed Immortall Fame.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O let them be as Heauens bright ſhining ſtarres,</l>
                  <l>That are my Friends, his true <note n="*" place="margin">I haue 70. Commiſſioners and 40. almoſt are of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, I hope one good <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees</hi> among them, will ſtand vp in my cauſe.</note> Commiſſioners,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as ſeeke to fruſtrate his Decree,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Darius</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezra.</hi> 6. 11. 12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> Sentence light on them for me,</l>
                  <l>Or turne their hearts, that they may rightly know,</l>
                  <l>I am thy Houſe, ſo builded long agoe;</l>
                  <l>With State, with Honor, and Endowments plenty,</l>
                  <l>Though Woluiſh times, and Men haue made it ſcanty;</l>
                  <l>For buriall of the dead, for pious vſes,</l>
                  <l>And not for <note n="b" place="margin">Gods Houſe was wont to be had in reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but I and my Courts are made a place of Sir-reuerence, and as baſe as any Layſtall, &amp;c.</note> Prophanation and abuſes;</l>
                  <l>That ſo men may haue better conſcience</l>
                  <l>To vſe me (like Gods houſe) with Reuerence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And let thoſe baſe, prophane, and idle Rout,</l>
                  <l>That daily paſſe with burthens, in, and out;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that <note n="c" place="margin">Such as I here meane loue neither Mother Churches, nor reuerend Fathers: They make a faire tall ſhew of Faith, but (as Maypoles) they grow ſlenderer and ſlenderer, till they come to bee Weather-Cockes, and then their Faith turnes with euery winde, and ſo be like the Tree that was hewen downe and caſt into the fire; hauing neither Roor, Rinde, Sap, Bough, Branch, Leafe, Bloſſome, or Fruit of good Workes, &amp;c.</note> deride me with their ſcoffes and Songs,</l>
                  <l>That wiſh my downefall with their ſpitefull tongues,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe hollow vpright Maypoles that doe hate,</l>
                  <l>To ſee their Mother Church be fortunate;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that haue ſuckt my Breſts till all is drye,</l>
                  <l>And yet are backward me to dignifie;</l>
                  <l>All that pollute my ſacred Courts and Walles,</l>
                  <l>Know there's a ſcourge for them, whenſe're it fals;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> O whip them ſoundly that abuſe thy Temple,</l>
                  <l>That others may be warn'd by their Example.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Heare me thy Sion, from thy Sanctuary,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Helpe me (O God) make haſte and doe not tary.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Sic Opto, ſic Oro.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>This is another Prayer or Petition, for the King, Prince, &amp;c. and directed to the <hi>Prince of Princes.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>O</l>
                  <l>Chriſt the Sonne of God,</l>
                  <l>Alpha and Omega,</l>
                  <l>Ruler of heauen and earth,</l>
                  <l>Orderer of all things,</l>
                  <l>Light of lights,</l>
                  <l>Very God of very God,</l>
                  <l>Sauiour of the world;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Preſerue the King and Prince, <note place="margin">I was cured of the Kings Euill by his gracious comming, and I hope (if he come once more) I ſhall be cured of the Wolfe and Dropſie, and preſerued from feare of the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sickneſſe.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reſtore my Fame,</l>
                  <l>Iuſtifie my Friends,</l>
                  <l>Nullifie my Foes,</l>
                  <l>Cure all my euils and infirmities,</l>
                  <l>Endow me with plenty,</l>
                  <l>Proſper great Britaine,</l>
                  <l>Send peace to all Chriſtendome.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the God of peace, &amp;c. make you perfect in all good workes, &amp;c.</hi> So be it. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>This is a Petition to the Kings Maieſtie onely.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I hope to ſee the 26. day of March to be ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated as a holy day for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer at my Croſſe, for a Thankſgiuing to the Lord that he ſtirred vp the heart of my good King to viſit me, &amp; to take courſe for my good, and then will there be 3. holy daies of great ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity togither: viz. March. 24 Coronation day. 25. Anun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation day 26. Viſitation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paules.</hi>
                  </note>
               </head>
               <p>I Humbly beſeech: Whereas vpon the 26. day of March laſt paſt, (being then Mid-Lent Sunday) it pleaſed your Maieſty (after the royall ſolemnity held vpon your Coronation day, and the Anun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of our bleſſed Lady, &amp;c.) to viſit me with your Sacred preſence in an honorable Aſſembly; and to declare your Kingly loue towards my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triumphant eſtate by your own gracious ſpeeches, and by the diuine Oratory of my Reuerend Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan at that inſtant, and ſoone after by a moſt Noble Commiſſion, &amp;c. For the which all people (my good Friends) that haue heard thereof, doe heartily honour and applaud your Highneſſe, as a ſecond <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That likewiſe it may pleaſe your Maieſty (now in this holy time of Lent, or ſome other time in the Interim of this high and moſt Honorable Court of Parliament at this preſent holden) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new <note place="margin">If a competent ſumme were in caſh, and Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds ſetting vp, and a Regiſter appointed for a record of mens Beneuolences, as in S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Bodleis</hi> Library, I ſhould not feare the wanr of money du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or euer after.</note> your pious fauour towards mee, by gaining ſome little beneuolence to ſet on the worke, as a free Offering or gift, and for redreſſe of my into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable wrongs, by ſome penall Lawes, and ſeuere puniſhment of the offenders.</p>
               <p>And I ſhall continue my praiers for your ſacred Maieſtie, your Princely Poſterity, your long, peaceable, and proſperous Reigne; and for that Noble, Reuerend, and Worthy Aſſembly (by the helpe of my Well-willers) to the worlds end. And this poore man (who hath beene my volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb facs="tcp:15065:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeruant theſe 8. yeares, by Bookes, Petitions, and other deuiſes, euen to his owne dilapidations) will (according to his bounden duty) approue himſelfe your Maieſties loyall Subiect, and my faithfull Proficient during life, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>St. <hi>Paules her Conceipt after this Petition.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF many Molehils, Mountaines may be made,</l>
                  <l>By many Springs, great Riuers we doe ſee,</l>
                  <l>By many hands a Burthen's light tis ſaid,</l>
                  <l>That (for ſome few) too waighty ſeemes to bee;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So many hands might make quicke worke of mee:</l>
                  <l>Though hard it ſeeme at firſt (moſt Royall King)</l>
                  <l>Yet once begunne t'will proue an eaſie thing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And rather benefit then loſſe.</l>
                  <l>For ſo ſhall many worke and pay their debts,</l>
                  <l>And what rich Subiects giues, poore Subiects gets:</l>
                  <l>No Money goes out of Thy Land thereby,</l>
                  <l>Or from the Chamber, or Thy Treaſury:</l>
                  <l>But all to offer freely at a Cheſt, <note place="margin">One little free Beneuolence to begin, will be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous then 1000. forced Collections or Taxations.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>What gifts they pleaſe, as at a Mariage Feaſt;</l>
                  <l>So Mites to Millions at the laſt may riſe,</l>
                  <l>And I be made a Princely Edifice.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here followeth a Petition written in my name, and preſented to the King, two dayes before his Maieſtie came to viſit me,</hi> (viz) <hi>on Friday the</hi> 24. <hi>of March</hi> 1619. <hi>But the Maſter of Requeſts then attending, tooke it away from his Highneſſe before he could reade it, as many things had beene ſo taken before, to the great hindrance and griefe of the poore Author.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:11"/>
            <head>To the KINGS moſt Sacred MAIESTIE.</head>
            <p>VVHereas (to the exeeeding great ioy of all my deare Friends, there is certaine intelligence giuen, that your Highneſſe will viſit me on Sunday next: And the rather I beleeue it, for that I haue had more ſweeping, bruſhing and cleanſing, then in 40. yeares before. <note place="margin">My workmen lookt like him they call Muld-Sacke after ſweeping of a Chimney.</note>
            </p>
            <q>May it pleaſe your moſt Excellent Maieſtie (among your royall Intendments to be celebrated in me vpon that Holy day) to manifeſt (withall) your pious Affection towards Repayre of my Decayes, and I ſhall daily pray, &amp;c.</q>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Authors Conceipt written vnder my PETITION.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAVLES (O King) ſince I her ſuite began, <note place="margin">This (for 500. li.) my Author can approue by oath that it came to me by my Complaint, which he made, that put M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                        <hi>Parker</hi> (a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor) in mind to do me good, as handſell to bring on more good Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>hath gain'd by fiue (almoſt) eight hundred pound;</l>
                  <l>Grace thou her Suite, and I'me aſſured than,</l>
                  <l>each hundred will a thouſand pounds be found;</l>
                  <l>Each thouſand, ten; and euery ten, a ſcore,</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe breake forth in thankes, and craue no more.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Petition to the</hi> PRINCE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ONe onely Aduocate with God we haue,</l>
                  <l>(Chriſt Ieſus, our ſweet Sauiour, his deare Sonne)</l>
                  <l>By whom alone we get all things we craue,</l>
                  <l>in humbleneſſe, and iuſt petition;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great <hi>Prince,</hi> you are my Soueraignes onely Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Reſemble then the Courſe twixt God and man,</l>
                  <l>And grace my humble ſuite the beſt you can;</l>
                  <l>And (as I'me bound) ſo will I euer pray,</l>
                  <l>That God will bleſſe your Highneſſe night and day.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Petition to the Right Honourable, the Lords of his MAIESTIES moſt <hi>Honorable Priuy Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FOR his ſake which (for your ſakes) once did cry <hi>Eli, Eli, lamaſabacthani;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For their ſakes, which (for Gods ſake) did not ſpare</l>
               <l>Or paines, or coſt, or ought, for my welfare;</l>
               <l>For all your Honors ſakes, I humbly craue,</l>
               <l>That now (if euer) I your helpes may haue:</l>
               <l>My Suite is honeſt, iuſt and reaſonable,</l>
               <l>The Worke is good, the End moſt honorable:</l>
               <l>Wherefore if you ſhall pleaſe to ſpeake for mee,</l>
               <l>Ile pray that heauen your dwelling place may be.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors now as aforeſaid, and alſo when you haue ended your labours, if you pleaſe (as ſome of your forefathers haue done) to reſt with me. <hi>S. PAVLES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:12"/>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> PAVLES <hi>concludeth in an Extaſie, alluded to the ſenſe of hearing, being as it were rauiſhed with ioy of her hopefull ſucceſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHat Wight is he in <hi>England-Iſra-el,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That knowes my wants, loues me, and can ſpeake well?</l>
               <l>Let him ſtand vp with Zeale and ſound intent,</l>
               <l>And ſpeake for me now in this <hi>Parliament;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is he a Leuite, Prieſt, Samaritan?</l>
               <l>Hath he the voice of Angell, or of man?</l>
               <l>Who ſhould he be (ſweete ſenſe doe not thou erre)</l>
               <l>Which doth in that high Court my Bill preferre?</l>
               <l>O, now I know; hearke how the people ſing,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory to God, and honor to the King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'ſt He indeed? is it that peereleſſe Iemme?</l>
               <l>(BEST OF BEST SPEAKERS IN IERVSALEM.)</l>
               <l>I'ſt He that holds me ſtill in Reuerence?</l>
               <l>I'ſt He that gets me a Beneuolence?</l>
               <l>I'ſt He that (for my good) lifts vp his Voice?</l>
               <l>And doe the people thus for me reioyce?</l>
               <l>Bleſſed be ſuch a King, and bleſſed all</l>
               <l>That thus doe honor me their Church of <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus much (for the moſt part) of what was giuen to the King on Midlent-Sunday laſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Here follow other things of the Author, done long before, and not impertinent to that which is herein intended (that is) to ſtirre vp good mindes to ſet forwards a good worke. <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Certaine Additions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Voyces and Viſions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Speeches and Parley,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Twixt</hi> Paules <hi>and</hi> Farley.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>As they haue beene giuen to the King at ſundry times, but not till now publiſhed.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S. PAVLES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST, recite to mee in briefe the Dreame or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thou hadſt after thou didſt publiſh my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, which thou didſt preſent to his Maieſty by a picture, and which picture thou intendedſt to haue giuen to his Maieſtie, if thy Petition had not fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>FARLEY.</speaker>
               <p>It was a Dreame in three parts.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The firſt ſhewing the King, <note n="*" place="margin">This was in the life time of our gracious Q. <hi>Anne,</hi> and came to paſſe (in ſome part) the ſaid 26. day of March, 1619.</note> Queene, and Prince; with all the Nobles, Reuerend Biſhops, and Clergy; Lord Mayor, Aldermen, Citizens,
<pb facs="tcp:15065:13"/> and people, comming as from the Tower (in great ſtate and ſolemnitie) to offer for your good at a Cheſt ſtanding at your great North-dore.</p>
               <p>In this Dreame (me thought) I ſaw preſents of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide queſo, &amp;c.</hi> 1. Kings Chap. 5. verſ. 8. 9. 10. &amp;c. all the chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> ſtone and timber ſent by forreigne Princes, to congratulate with his Maieſtie in that pious work intended for your reparation as * <hi>Hiram</hi> ſent to King <hi>Salomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo (me thought) I ſaw a Poſie written in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall letters ouer your Gate next Cheapſide, to this effect; <hi>viz. BEHOLD THE KING COMETH WITH GREAT IOY, &amp;c.</hi> And (me thought) I ſaw a great glory in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and heard two voices ſounding in my eares, one towards the King thus, <hi>For thy Temples ſake, &amp;c. I wiſh thee all proſperity:</hi> The other voice ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding towards the midle of the <hi>city</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Many good things are done in thee, ô thou faire City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Dreame ſhewing the royall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities <note place="margin">This part of my Dreame hath alſo proued true.</note> at the Offering, and you in that ragged poore, and ſmoaky caſe, as now you are, and the King, &amp;c. ſitting to heare a Sermon in the ſame very Window and place where his Maieſtie did ſit indeed when He came to viſit you.</p>
               <p>Me thought I ſaw (among all your Grieuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that then were opened to his Maieſties ſight and hearing) one thing written in Capitall letters, which was well obſerued on all parts, (viz.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VIEW, O KING, HOW MY WALL-CREEPERS,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAVE MADE ME WORKE FOR CHIMNEY-SWEEPERS.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p> The Pſalme that was ſung before the Sermon was (me thought) the <note n="*" place="margin">Vide.</note> 122. Pſalme.</p>
               <p>The Text was out of the 24. Chapter of the ſecond Booke of <hi>Chron.</hi> the 10. verſe <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And all the Lords and all the people reioiced, and brought in, and caſt into the Cheſt, vntill there was ſufficient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Preacher (me thought) was that Reuerend <note place="margin">This approued true in part.</note> Biſhop of this Dioceſſe, whoſe lot was afterward to performe that taske in another Text appointed by his Sacred Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Me thought he diuided the Text aforeſaid thus, <hi>The Lords and People reioiced, and brought in, and caſt into the Cheſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They not onely brought in and caſt into the Cheſt (ſaid he) but they alſo <hi>reioyced,</hi> for ſo (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) God is well pleaſed, who accepteth and loueth a <hi>Cheerefull giuer,</hi> and the cheerefulneſſe of the <hi>Giuer</hi> doth much commend the <hi>Gift.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then he obſerued the readineſſe of the People by the particle, <hi>All.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not ſome of the Lords, or ſome of the people offered, but <hi>All</hi> the Lords, and <hi>All</hi> the People, euen the poore Widow caſt in her <hi>Mite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the peoples continuance in well doing. For (ſaid he) they gaue not a little at the firſt for faſhion ſake, or in ſhew of deuotion, and then grew weary, but they brought in and caſt into the Cheſt, <hi>vntill there was ſufficient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therein he alſo obſerued, how the End crowns the Action, for to beginne well, and not to end well is to bee a Chriſtian by halfes, and that in
<pb facs="tcp:15065:14"/> the worſt halfe too.</p>
               <p>And theſe (mee thought) were the principall diuiſions of the Text, whereat I was neuer a whit vext, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>After the Sermon was ended, I went in, and at two of your Pillars neare Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Hattons</hi> Tombe (me thought) I ſaw two Cheſts, chained to two Pillars, one hauing theſe words and verſes in Capitall letters written in a faire Table, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ouer the Cheſt as followeth, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div type="section">
               <head>THE KINGS CHEST.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>COme all good Subiects loyall, and liege people,</l>
                  <l>With chearful harts to help this Church and Steeple,</l>
                  <l>For here's the place of offering appointed</l>
                  <l>By IAMES our ſacred King, and Gods Annointed:</l>
                  <l>Where ſuch as (with deuotion) offer free,</l>
                  <l>Shall in true Regiſter recorded be,</l>
                  <l>To their great honor, fame, renowne and praiſe,</l>
                  <l>From this time forward, to the end of dayes:</l>
                  <l>His Highneſſe hath begunne for your example,</l>
                  <l>Come then I pray it's for Gods holy Temple.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>THE QVEENES CHEST.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis Cheſt, which here inchained you doe finde,</l>
                  <l>(Prepared for the gifts of <note n="*" place="margin">Or kind Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> women-kinde)</l>
                  <l>Queen ANNE (chiefe foundreſſe, &amp; S. <hi>Paules</hi> wel-willer)</l>
                  <l>Commanded to be fixed to this pillar,</l>
                  <l>And 'cauſe ſhe would her pious heart vnfold,</l>
                  <l>Shee firſt put in a Princely ſhowre of gold.</l>
                  <l>Come Ladies then, her goodneſſe imitate,</l>
                  <l>And let <hi>Paules</hi> know ſhee ſhall be fortunate.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l> Nay come all women, bring away your crownes,</l>
                  <l>Pounds, ſhillings, pence, from Countries, Cities, Townes:</l>
                  <l>O let it be to all a ioy and pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>To helpe this Church with ſome part of your treaſure:</l>
                  <l>It is a bleſſed worke, and well't doth ſuite,</l>
                  <l>That faithfull trees ſhould bring forth holy fruite.</l>
                  <l>Your Offerings ſhall be kept in true Record,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the ſecond comming of the Lord.</l>
                  <l>Come then (I pray) and let this Prouerbe ſtand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When Women giue they haue a luckie hand.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>Theſe two Cheſts, one for the men, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the womens Offerings (me thought) one told me, were placed there, not ſo much for the preſent Offering, (which was then in generall at your North doore, for getting money to ſet on the Worke) but for future, during the time of your Reparation, and were attended by one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the King of purpoſe to <note n="*" place="margin">This Regiſter or Record, is humbly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by, &amp;c. as a Grace to what he hath done.</note> record the gifts which ſhould be brought in, either as volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the liuing, or as Legatory by the deceaſed; To the end his Maieſtie might once a yeare ſee how his louing Subiects, and loyall people did ſecond his Highneſſe, and imitate his goodneſſe (to their power) in his pious deſignes.</p>
               <p>And thus I concluded my ſecond Dreame, <hi>viz. As wicked workes doe bring our ſoules damnation, So pious workes are ſteps to our ſaluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. My third and laſt Dreame was in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Me thought I ſaw you ſuddenly renewed, beautifully repaired, and cured of all your euills, and infirmities.</p>
               <p>And then (me thought) appeared a farre more
<pb facs="tcp:15065:15"/> glorious ſplendor in the Heauens then that which I ſaw in my firſt Dreame, and neare to the Kings Picture, (which (me thought) was rarely ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and cut in ſtone vpon your Steeple) I ſaw eight Angels flying vp and downe, reioycing with great melody, and ſounding Praiſes with Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets and heauenly Voices as followeth: <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>For this good worke King <hi>Iames</hi> ſhall rule in peace,</l>
                  <l>And 'cauſe (by him) the Goſpell doth increaſe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Hee ſhall be proſperous in all his wayes,</l>
                  <l>Hee ſhall haue health, long life, and happy dayes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>His Royall Seede ſhall mighty be and many,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall increaſe as much as ere did any.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Hee ſhall plant Colonies in euery Nation,</l>
                  <l>To forward ſtill the Goſpels propagation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Like as the Sands on Sea, or Starres in Skye,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall his People grow and multiply.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="6">
                  <head>6 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Hee ſhall haue conqueſt when hee goes to fight,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall put all his enemies to flight:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="7">
                  <head>7 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>And (at the laſt) to end our bleſſed ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Hee ſhall be crown'd in heauen with endleſſe glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="8">
                  <head>8 <hi>Angell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Where Angels and Archangels euer ſings</l>
                  <l>All prayſe and honor to the King of Kings.</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>So be it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <p>Amen.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> This glorious ſound of the Angels, ſo much inflamed my ſpirits with diuine deſires to heare and ſee more, (being alſo rapt and rauiſhed with ioy at your beautifull appearance) that I ſuddenly ſtart vp in my bed, and was thereby awaked.</p>
                  <p>And thus haue I ended my third Dreame, and as briefly as I could repeated all three of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you not write a Booke of this at large, and giue it to his Maieſtie when you preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Table?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes that I did, but for want of a Friend in Court, I failed of my deſires, which was, to haue publiſhed it; ſuch ill ſucceſſe had I with my Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that (although) his Maieſtie ſeemed well pleaſed with any thing I gaue him in your behalfe, yet could I neuer get Reference vpon any: So that oftentimes I went by Chearing <hi>(aliàs</hi> Charing Croſſe) in the Morning, and home by weeping Croſſe at night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>What time of the yeare did you fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe contemplatiue Dreames?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <p>Vpon the Eue of S. <hi>Iames</hi> the Apoſtle it beganne, but it continued long after, as you ſhall ſee by the <hi>Prologue,</hi> which is before the Dreame in the Booke which I gaue to the King, in this manner;</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The PROLOGVE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVpon the Feaſt of IAMES th'Apoſtle laſt,</l>
                  <l>At ten a clocke i'th night, and ſomewhat paſt;</l>
                  <l>I went to bed, and after I had pray'd,</l>
                  <l>I turnd me on my right ſide, and ſo laid;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:16"/>
                  <l> Intending there in quiet ſort to ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the Larke did ſing, or day did peepe;</l>
                  <l>So muſing broad awake a little while,</l>
                  <l>At laſt a ſlumber did mine eyes beguile;</l>
                  <l>And what I thought but then, before I ſlept,</l>
                  <l>I dream'd thereon, and in that Dreame was kept</l>
                  <l>Foure houres at leaſt, nay (as I now remember)</l>
                  <l>It did not end vntill the laſt Nouember;</l>
                  <l>Except ſome thrice, and then I felt ſome paine;</l>
                  <l>So dream'd, ſo wak't, then dream't, then wak't againe,</l>
                  <l>As if I had beene <note n="*" place="margin">It might haue made a better head then mine ake aboue three times.</note> made of dreame and ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes I laught, and ſometimes waile and weepe,</l>
                  <l>By which I cal'd to mind a ſacred Theame,</l>
                  <l>That all mans life is but a Sleepe or Dreame,</l>
                  <l>A Span, a Flower, a Ship at Sea, a Bubble;</l>
                  <l>Like to a Tale that's told, like Graſſe, like Stubble;</l>
                  <l>Like any thing that ſoone doth change and fade,</l>
                  <l>Such is the life of man, whom God hath made;</l>
                  <l>I meane in this life, fraile and tranſitory,</l>
                  <l>Vntill he doe attaine the life of glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>And then beganne my waking dreaming Story.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I pray thee repeate the Conceipt thou madeſt in my name, which thou gaueſt to the Lord Mayor of London, when thou didſt preſent my Complaint vnto him, a little after Chriſtmas. 1615.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <p>I will giue you the effect as well as I can remember. (viz.)</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir</hi> Iohn Iolles <hi>Knight, Lord Mayor, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It was in his time, &amp;c.</note>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The Humble Petition of</hi> H. F. <hi>for S.</hi> Paules <hi>Church in London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas it is a laudable Cuſtome in this Honourable Citie, that about this time in euery yeare, the Alderman of euery Ward doth preſent vnto the Lord Mayor (for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) all abuſes, miſdemeanours, annoyances and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes, to the end they ſhould be reformed, auoyded and amended.</p>
            <p>It may pleaſe your good Lordſhip (in regard that no Ward-mote Inqueſt hath as yet taken notice of my decayes and annoyances,) to accept of this my Preſentment made by my Friend, and to doe to mee <note place="margin">His anſwer was Honorable and worthy at that time.</note> what honorable fauour and reſpect you can towards my redreſſe: And I ſhall pray, &amp;c.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Set downe likewiſe, the Letter which you deuiſed in my name to the Reuerend Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers that come to my Croſſe, for it will not bee impertinent to be inſerted.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall gladly doe it as followeth. (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>MY very Reuerend Friends, you are the Lords Ambaſſadors, whom therfore ſhould you feare? You ſee before your eyes my miſerable eſtate, how (of the faireſt Caedar in Lebanon) I am become the leaſt reſpected in London. Like a great withering Oake
<pb facs="tcp:15065:17"/> in a greene flouriſhing Forreſt, and of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable See-farre, a forlorne, and a forſaken Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher; your Wiſedomes know I haue raiſed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained many; O then let me not be forgotten in mine old age: you know likewiſe, that Briefe vpon Briefe goes currant for the reſtauration of the prophane houſes of men, which haue been ruined by misfortune of fire, as I was, and how they are new builded and made better then before. I hope therefore you will do ſomewhat for Gods houſe. You giue thanks for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits that are beſtowed on them that come with the Lords Ambaſſage to my Croſſe: And pray for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſuch benefactors. I deſire that you would pray likewiſe for ſuch Benefactors as will contribute to my good; that ſo the Church and Churchmen may thriue together. For the houſes of men there are <hi>prouiſoes</hi> and <hi>Couenants</hi> to tie the Tenants to reparation, or to forfeit their Leaſes: are there no ſuch <hi>Prouiſoes</hi> and <hi>Couenants</hi> for Gods Tenants? If there be not, then ſure it is becauſe hee holds them ſo worthy that they need not be bound: I ſay no more, becauſe I doubt not of your loue and care. And ſo I commend you to the heauenly protection of the Almighty, and reſt in ſilence euer hereafter as your louing Mother-Church,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>S. Paules.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now ſet downe what other things you thinke fit, and let vs draw to concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then firſt I will write the Carroll which I gaue to his Maieſtie on Chriſtmas day, before his going into Scotland (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>IN Paradiſe was <hi>Adam</hi> borne;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> but in a Stall:</l>
               <l>By the firſt we were forlorne,</l>
               <l>by the ſecond ſaued all:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory be to God on High,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioy at Chriſts Natiuitie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God preſerue your Maieſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euah</hi> out of <hi>Adam</hi> came,</l>
               <l>Chriſt of <hi>Mary</hi> tooke his birth,</l>
               <l>By the firſt came woe and ſhame,</l>
               <l>by the ſecond ioy on earth;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glory be to God on High, &amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Peace be ſtill within thy wals,</l>
               <l>Plenty to all needy ſoules,</l>
               <l>So (good King) remember <hi>Paules.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:18"/>
               <p>This following I gaue to his Maieſty when he tooke Coach at Theobalds, in his Highneſſe Progreſſe to Scotland aforeſaid, as my faithfull Farewell or faire wiſh to the good ſucceſſe of his Sacred Maieſtie, and of all his Noble, Reuerend, and Worthy followers, &amp;c. viz.</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>RIde on with honor (mighty King)</l>
               <l>With Princely high Renowne,</l>
               <l>From <hi>London</hi> vnto <note n="*" place="margin">It may well be called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, or a place of Ioy where ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Peacema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker was borne.</note> 
                  <hi>Edenburgh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy natiue Seate and Towne:</l>
               <l>And bleſſed be thy Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>In euery place thou goeſt,</l>
               <l>Vnto the ioy of Man and Boy,</l>
               <l>From higheſt to the loweſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ride on yee Noble Lords alſo,</l>
               <l>God bleſſe you and our Maſter,</l>
               <l>And in the Progreſſe as yee paſſe,</l>
               <l>Defend you from diſaſter:</l>
               <l>And Trinity in Vnitie,</l>
               <l>Be ſtill your guide and glory;</l>
               <l>That of this time each penne may rime,</l>
               <l>A pleaſant Progreſſe ſtory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ride yee on, yee Reu'rend ones,</l>
               <l>For you are for our ſoules;</l>
               <l>And when you are at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I pray remember <hi>Paules:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſhee will pray both night and day</l>
               <l>For your proſperitie;</l>
               <l>Becauſe your words much helpe affords,</l>
               <l>In her neceſſitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>Ride on likewiſe, yee worthy Knights,</l>
               <l>With Iovialty and pleaſure,</l>
               <l>And ſee you haue a noble eare</l>
               <l>To bring againe our <note n="*" place="margin">No nation can haue a greater Treaſure in a Prudent and a gracious King then we haue, if wee were ſo thankfull to God as we ought to be.</note> Treaſure:</l>
               <l>Your fealty and loyalty,</l>
               <l>The Lord will euer bleſſe,</l>
               <l>And for the ſame you ſhall get fame,</l>
               <l>And heauenly happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So ride yee on his Officers,</l>
               <l>And Yeomen ſtrong and truſty;</l>
               <l>Some guard before, and ſome behinde,</l>
               <l>Be valiant, bold and luſty:</l>
               <l>Yet ſee you be for Courtiſie</l>
               <l>In <hi>Scotland</hi> well commended:</l>
               <l>That loue and peace may ſtill increaſe</l>
               <l>vntill the world be ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as in Progreſſe ſo in Regreſſe,</l>
               <l>O, let vs euer pray,</l>
               <l>That God will bleſſe his Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>And Queene and Prince alway:</l>
               <l>That North, and Weſt, and South, and Eaſt,</l>
               <l>His glory wee may ſing,</l>
               <l>And nights and dayes giue thanks and praiſe,</l>
               <l>For IAMES our Sacred King.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now followeth a</hi> Welcome <hi>to his</hi> MAIESTIE, <hi>as I intended to preſent the ſame at</hi> Windſor, <hi>but was hindered of my purpoſe. (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>VVElcome Dread Soueraigne from that Paradiſe,</l>
               <l>Where Nature gaue thee Birth, Grace, Edifice:</l>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Great Britaines</hi> Treaſure, and beſt Iemme,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to our <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Peace-maker,</hi> Louer of Vnitie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europes</hi> admired King for Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>And for all Vertues that good Kings befit,</l>
               <l>As Mercy, Iuſtice, Learning, Wiſedome, Wit.</l>
               <l>Welcome tenne thouſand times, and bleſſed be</l>
               <l>All thoſe that (with <hi>true hearts)</hi> doe welcome Thee,</l>
               <l>And all thy Noble, and thy faithfull Traine,</l>
               <l>That went with Thee, and brought Thee ſafe againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such ioy ſucceed thy trauels to the North,</l>
               <l>That thereby peace and concord may ſpring forth,</l>
               <l>And ſpread it ſelfe throughout great <hi>Britany,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To the perfecting of true Amitie.</l>
               <l>That ſo from Eaſt to Weſt, from North to South,</l>
               <l>Gods praiſe, and Thine, may be in euery mouth.</l>
               <l>And to thy meeting with thy Turtle Royall,</l>
               <l>(Thy ſacred ſecond ſelfe, thy Queene moſt Loyall)</l>
               <l>Thy Princely Son, (our High and Mighty CHARLES,)</l>
               <l>Thy Noble Councellors, Lords, Ladies, Earles,</l>
               <l>Biſhops, Clergy, Knights, Gentry, Commons, All</l>
               <l>That long haue wiſh'd thy preſence at <hi>Whitehall:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thy true Citizens of famous <hi>London,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That (for thy abſence) thought themſelues vndon;</l>
               <l>Such ioy ſucceed as neuer was before,</l>
               <l>And God increaſe that ioy for euermore.</l>
               <l>And as I pray, ſo pray all loyall people,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neuer forgetting</hi> S. Paules <hi>Church and Steeple.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This following is another Chriſtmas Caroll which I gaue to his Maieſtie on the Chriſtmas day next after his Highneſſe Returne from</hi> Scotland.</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THe <note n="a" place="margin">This day we were ſaued from eternall death.</note> fiue and twentieth of December,</l>
               <l>And the <note n="b" place="margin">This day from a ſudden fearefull, and a moſt inhumane death.</note> fift day of Nouember,</l>
               <l>Let vs thankefully remember;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with ioy for euer ſing,</l>
               <l>Praiſes to our heauenly King,</l>
               <l>and be doing ſome good thing:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Glory be to God on High,</l>
               <l>For our Chriſts Natiuitie, <note place="margin">Nothing can be more remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then <hi>Pauls</hi> Repaire, in thankfull me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of our wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuery from the Gunpowder Treaſon.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And our great Deliuery.</l>
               <l>God preſerue your Maiestie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Peace be ſtill within Thy wals,</l>
               <l>Plenty to all needy Soules;</l>
               <l>Now (good King) remember <hi>Paules.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Here my Candle was cleane burnt out, and this laſt Caroll, was the laſt thing I preſented to his Maieſtie, vntill two dayes before His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to viſit you, (which was the Petition before recited.) In this Interim I grew much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed, for that I ſaw little hope of your helpe; many rubs I rannne through, many ſcoffes and ſcornes I did vndergoe; forſaken by my Butterflie
<pb facs="tcp:15065:20"/> Friends, laught and derided at by your Enemies; <note place="margin">Let them that ſcoffe at this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of Sureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> purſued after by <hi>Wolues of Wood-ſtreet,</hi> and the <hi>Foxes of the Poultrey,</hi> ſometimes ſtrongly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred, and ſometimes at the point of Death and Deſpaire: In ſtead of ſeruing my <hi>Prince,</hi> which I humbly deſired, (though but as a doore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper in you) I was preſt for the ſeruice of King <hi>Lud,</hi> where all the comfort I had, was, that I could ſee you, ſalute you, and condole with your miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: my poore cloathes and ragges I could not compare to any thing better then to your Weſt End; and my ſeruice to nothing leſſe then bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: So I was troubled in my ſleepes, and drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med I heard fearefull voices ſounding in, and about you, which were as follow. (viz.)</p>
            <p>The firſt voice (me thought) was in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which now is beautified and repaired by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Raphe Chamberlein,</hi> and made a place of <note n="*" place="margin">It lay before like a Swine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, with duſt, rubbiſh, and ſoote, and the windowes as if Hags and Hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goblins had torne them.</note> morning Sacrifice to the Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <p>Where a gaſtly Ghoſt ſtart vp out of an old Tombe or Graue, and ſaid thus:</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>HAd I and my Forefathers thus neglected,</l>
               <l>To ſee Gods houſes mended and erected;</l>
               <l>Or for to giue of rich Endowments plenty,</l>
               <l>That none which did his ſeruice might goe empty;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> Where had his Word beene taught, to me expreſſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An.</hi> In vncouth places, Caues, and Wilderneſſe.</l>
               <l>"O then repaire what to your hands we builded,</l>
               <l>"Leſt all your workes proue painted ſhewes ore gilded.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then another Ghoſt appeared neare that which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Duke</hi> Humphries <hi>Tombe, and made a voice like the voice of Pitty. (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen Winter with his blaſts, flouds, froſts and ſnow,</l>
               <l>Hath made all things looke old, and dead to ſee;</l>
               <l>In comes the Spring: ſo once a yeare you know,</l>
               <l>All Caedars, ſhrubs, and plants renued be:</l>
               <l>O thankleſſe man, is God thus good to thee?</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou then neglect his good example,</l>
               <l>In many Springs not to renew his Temple.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <p>Another ſtarts vp vnder the Arches of the Conſiſtory where the Lawyers get Fees, and ſayes thus in anſwere of Pitty.</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Cauſes why, <note place="margin">This was <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Ile ſoone diſcry;</l>
               <l>For when men ſtriue themſelues to magnifie,</l>
               <l>To flaunt in worldly pompe and rich aray,</l>
               <l>They doe forget Gods houſe to dignifie,</l>
               <l>That's left to runne to ruine and decay,</l>
               <l>Alas, alas, alas, and welladay:</l>
               <l>The time hath beene when ſuch a famous Church,</l>
               <l>Could not (for want of Friends) bin left i'th lurch.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <p>Then ſpake Zeale out of the two Towers at the Weſt End (viz.) Lollords Tower, and the Tower where yeur trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ardent Zeale</hi> two voices.</note> was kept in a hole of your wall. (viz.)</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Voice. </seg>1</label> TO ſee a ſtrange out-landiſh Fowle, </l>
               <l>A quaint Baboon, an Ape, an Owle,</l>
               <l>A dancing Beare, a Gyants bone,</l>
               <l>A fooliſh Ingin moue alone,</l>
               <l>A Morris-dance, a Puppit play,</l>
               <l>Mad <hi>Tom</hi> to ſing a Roundelay,</l>
               <l>A Woman dancing on a Rope;</l>
               <l>Bull-baiting alſo at the <hi>Hope;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15065:21"/>
               <l> A Rimers Ieſts, a Iuglers cheats,</l>
               <l>A Tumbler ſhewing cunning feats,</l>
               <l>Or Players acting on the Stage,</l>
               <l>There goes the bounty of our Age:</l>
               <l>But vnto any pious motion,</l>
               <l>There's little coine, and leſſe deuotion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Voice. </seg>2</label> FOr euery faſhion baſe and vaine,</l>
               <l>For purchaſing, or greedy gaine,</l>
               <l>For <note n="*" place="margin">Let M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke</hi> thinke I reach no high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the Vulgar <hi>Vp-ſtart</hi> in theſe two lines, or the Prodigall ſpend-thrift: I cenſure not the Pleaſures and paſtimes of the truely Noble, and of all others that exerciſe any laudable ſports for Recreation of wit, and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of body.</note> Dicing, Drinking, fooliſh ſporting,</l>
               <l>Hunting, Wenching, Coaching, Courting,</l>
               <l>There is enough in euery Function,</l>
               <l>But to this Church is ſmall Compunction.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <argument>
               <p>This voice being ended, I awaked, and in an Impatient manner made this mine owne voice, as followeth. viz.</p>
            </argument>
            <lg>
               <l>IF it be ſo, farewell <hi>Britania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For I will goe vnto <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſee what Saluages will doe,</l>
               <l>When Chriſtians are ſo hard to wooe:</l>
               <l>Take heed all Writers in this kind,</l>
               <l>For Church Complaints are waſted wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So going to the Treaſurer for <hi>Virginia,</hi> with Reſolution to depart the Land with ſpeed; hee being not then at leiſure, appointed me to come <note place="margin">Vpon a Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in Lent.</note> the Wedneſday following: and at my returne from <hi>Alderſgate</hi> to your preſence againe, there came newes by a ſweet Weſterne gale of winde that his Maieſtie would certainly come to viſit you on Mid-Lent Sunday in great ſolemnity. At which moſt ioyfull Tidings I forgot <hi>Virginia</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and attended with hope of ſome happie ſuccceſſe, to my hearty deſires, towards your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration;
<pb facs="tcp:15065:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> which (I thanke the Lord) was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the full of my expectation for that time.</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>DOMINE SALVVM FAC REGEM IACOBVM.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus for your good I'ue written to the full,</l>
                  <l>Weari'd my <hi>Muſe,</hi> and made my ſpirits dull;</l>
                  <l>Spent time and Coyne (good God) what ſhall I more?</l>
                  <l>Onely a good Succeſſe I doe implore.</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S. Pa.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Be of good cheere, and let God worke his will,</l>
                     <l>Speake to the King, for he is Gracious ſtill,</l>
                     <l>If ſo thou canſt not either ſpeed or thriue</l>
                     <l>Let me alone, and doe no further ſtriue;</l>
                     <l>Thy Charges hath beene great I muſt confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Thy paines (likewiſe) I doe accept no leſſe,</l>
                     <l>Therefore when any good to me doth fall,</l>
                     <l>Be ſure my Loue ſhall proue Reciprocall:</l>
                     <l>And at the laſt, when <hi>Death</hi> ſhall ſtrike thee dead,</l>
                     <l>Within my Wombe thou ſhalt be buried:</l>
                     <l>Where (for thy kindneſſe vnto me expreſſed)</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt remaine, till Chriſt ſay, <hi>Come ye Bleſſed;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So to conclude, and make our Friends to laugh,</l>
                     <l>Ile tell thee what ſhall be thy Epitaph.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>(viz.)</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VNder this Stone, my <hi>HARRY</hi> lies interred,</l>
                     <l>Neuer till now, by <hi>Friends</hi> or <hi>Fates</hi> preferred,</l>
                     <l>For though by <hi>Death</hi> his Bodie's here in <hi>Duſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Soule's prefer'd among the <hi>Iuſt;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He (for my Good) did labour late and early,</l>
                     <l>His Chriſti'n Name you know, his Sirname's <hi>FARLEY:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15065:22"/>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I humbly thanke your</hi> Greatneſſe, <hi>and doe pray,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You may proue happy till the latter Day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Expect each</hi> 
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Or the</hi> 26. <hi>of March.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Mid-Lent Sunday while I liue,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Something (for you) Ile to my</hi> Soueragine <hi>giue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Veritate &amp; Reuerentia.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>Yea, becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our</p>
                  <p>God, I will ſeeke to do Thee good, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 122. 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed may that Preacher bee, That will pray and ſpeake for mee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:15065:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To the Courteous and Charitable</hi> Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ACcept my meaning (Worthy Friend)</l>
               <l>Although my wit be weake,</l>
               <l>And from the <hi>Crittickes</hi> me defend,</l>
               <l>If any 'gainſt me ſpeake.</l>
               <l>A Scholler I confeſſe I'm none,</l>
               <l>By Reading or by Art:</l>
               <l>But truly I loue euery one</l>
               <l>That is ſo, with my heart.</l>
               <l>When I the fayre <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> Mount</l>
               <l>To climbe was almoſt able,</l>
               <l>I fell too ſhort of my accompt,</l>
               <l>And went but to <hi>Dunce-table.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So like a Dunce I'ue writ this Booke,</l>
               <l>(With griefe I it reueale,)</l>
               <l>Where's naught <note n="*" place="margin">As touching Art or Scholer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> praiſe-worthy (if you looke)</l>
               <l>But onely my true <hi>Zeale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In which I vow to all good men,</l>
               <l>My loue to <hi>Paules</hi> is ſuch,</l>
               <l>That if I had an Angels pen</l>
               <l>I'de write tenne times as much:</l>
               <l>Or if of other Angels I</l>
               <l>Had (as ſome haue) great ſtore</l>
               <l>Shee ſhould not neede to begge or cry</l>
               <l>To King or People more.</l>
               <l>But of thoſe Angels laſt my Purſe</l>
               <l>Is too too thinne and bare;</l>
               <l>And euery day growes worſe and worſe</l>
               <l>As <hi>Paules</hi> her ſelfe doth fare.</l>
               <l>Therefore in me what here is ſcant</l>
               <l>Of Money, Art, or Wit:</l>
               <l>Doe thou ſupply vnto our Want,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So God bleſſe thee, and it.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy faithfull and thankfull Friend, H. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
